ph: 413-824-9414

mertz@gnosis.cx

SUMMARY

Software Engineer, Technologist, Speaker and Writer

I am a software developer, and a writer & researcher about programming topics. I have worked principally as a consultant with a variety of companies, often in ways combining these mentioned roles. As well, I have been very active in Open Source communities, especially around Python; I am a member of the Python Software Foundation, a Director of the PSF, chair of its Trademarks Committee, and chair of its Outreach & Education Committee. In a related capacity, I frequently speak at conferences, including OSCON and PyCon, and have given technical keynote talks at PyCon India, PyCon UK, PyCon-ZA, and PyCon-Belarus.

In development-oriented consulting projects, I have utilized my broad background to research and advance projects in natural language processing, data modeling, cryptography/security, information presentation and analysis, parsers and DSLs, data structures and databases. In general I am familiar with many programming technologies and tools, a quick learner, and comfortable choosing and using the most appropriate technology for a given project.

As a writer, I write as a practical programmer rather than as either a disinterested journalist or a theoretical computer scientist. My ongoing *Charming Python* column was, for 8 years, the most widely read discussion of the Python programming language worldwide. Articles and columns I write on other topics are also well known and well received. My Addison-Wesley book *Text Processing in Python* is a standard reference on its title topic, used in both industry and academia.

I can sling lines of code very well; moreover, I can explain technologies and techniques to team members and collaborators. I have a capacity to bring comparative and analytic perspective to development or documentation goals, and to assume a project lead role and facilitate work flow. I am well familiar with the tools and techniques around version control systems, project management, collaborative tools and wikis, unit and integrity testing tools, performance monitoring, and can evaluate a range of software and infrastructure options.

EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer and Technical Writer, D. E. Shaw Research, New York NY 2008-present

Documented programming interfaces to the Anton supercomputer. Worked with developers to consolidate, expand, clarify and organize documentation of the world's fastest supercomputer for research simulations in computational biochemistry. Work involves understanding a range of hardware issues and programming tools: custom assemblies, M4, C, C++, Python, RTL, simulation environments. As well, work with research chemists to understand motivations in physical sciences for DESRES hardware and software systems. Created an internal document-production tool chain using a variety of scripting and text processing tools.

Created and maintained a software tool, written in Python, to validate chemical simulation configurations. Worked with other users developers to create the queuing and job logging system used internally. Maintained and enhanced the external website which requires export validation of downloaders. Created tools to auto-generate embedded source code for the Anton computer. Created an in-house accounting front-end interface using Django and communicating with back-end data sources. Created a parsing tool to transform a custom specification language into C++, Verilog, and Python source code, and to generate documentation.

page 2

Senior Programmer/Consultant, Madison Tyler LLC, Beverly Hills CA 2006-2007

Worked at high-tech financial trading firm specializing in "black box" and "gray box" automated and computer-assisted trading. Primary development language was Python, with additional use of shell scripting, SQL and RDBMS optimization, Java, C/C++, and numerous other specialized tools. Responsible for analysis of latency and runtime efficiency issues. Developed in-house code related to computational linguistics, statistical modeling, pattern extraction, field-specific ontology, and real-time data processing. Created AJAX interfaces for user interaction with server-generated results.

Writer/Columnist, IBM developerWorks; Intel Developer Services; O'Reilly ONLamp, etc 2000-2011

Write articles well known in the Python and XML communities, and in other technical areas (cryptography, functional programming, Linux administration, networking, etc). Columns include *Charming Python* and *XML Matters*. Author of Addison-Wesley book *Text Processing in Python*. Publication history includes several hundred programming/technical articles. See http://gnosis.cx/publish for details.

Consultant, Gnosis Software, Los Angeles CA 1998-present

Freelance consultant on various projects, typically ones where an expertise in algorithms, data design, or general technologies is needed at a more sophisticated level than in-house staff can provide. Some recent clients/projects have included:

- *SEIU*, Washington DC. (2009-present). Generation of data, largely via web-scraping, for use in organizing campaigns.
- *Ripe Media*, Beverly Hills CA (2007). Developed Javascript library for enhanced user interaction on a portion of Grammy Award's web site. Debugged and tested against various platforms/browsers.
- Snowtide Informatics, Hadley MA (2006). Improved algorithmic structure of flagship product, PDFTextStream, leading to both greater accuracy and speed of PDF parsing and analysis. Programming performed in Python and Java.
- Polimetrix, Palo Alto CA (2005). Text processing and natural language processing problems for normalization of names and postal addresses. Assured strict conformance of processed results with USPS Pub28, even on approximate, incorrect, or poorly formatted input data.

Chief Technology Officer, Open Voting Consortium 2004-2008

Board member and technical advisor to non-profit organization devoted to providing fair and transparent voting technologies (openly inspectible source code and voter-verifiable paper ballots). Duties include code inspection, security analysis, development of licensing language, coding standards, press relations, promotion of frameworks to academic, press, and professional colleagues, and interaction with government bodies. Also served on the IEEE P1622 committee, *Voting Systems Electronic Data Interchange*. See http://openvoting.org/ for further details.

page 3

Senior Programmer, Human Technology Partnership, Greenfield MA 1995-1998

Maintained and upgraded existing software products used by major financial services companies, while simultaneously developing new product lines. Worked with legacy code in several xBase dialects (Clipper, Foxpro) and Pascal to provide client customization; performed much revamping of user interface and created better modularization, transportability, and especially internal documentation of existing code to streamline future customization. Also created several new information-centric products using various hypertext tools to develop computer-based training and reference works for commercial and custom markets.

Adjunct Professor, University of Hartford; University of Massachusetts; Massachusetts College of Liberal Arts 1990-1994

Developed curriculum and taught courses in medical ethics, general ethics, feminism, social and political philosophy, logic, epistemology, and general introduction to philosophy. Extensive academic publication in philosophy and related fields. See http://gnosis.cx/publish/resumes/cv.txt for details.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts at Amherst; Ph.D., Philosophy, 1999 University of Massachusetts at Amherst; M.A., Philosophy, 1992 University of Colorado at Boulder; B.A. Philosophy/Mathematics, 1987

SPECIALITIES

Technologies: Python; SQL/RDBMS; schema design; textual analysis; statistical natural language processing; XML and web technologies (Javascript, CSS, DHTML, etc.); data structures. Prior familiarity with large range of programming languages and tools, including Java; PHP; C/C++; Ruby; Perl; R; xBase dialects (Clipper, Foxpro, Fivewin, XBase++); Unix text tools (sed, awk, grep, tr, etc.); Pascal/Delphi; Fortran; Paradox PAL; Alpha Four; Basics (VB/VBA, RealBasic, etc.); REXX; TCL/TK; Bash; Lisp/Scheme; Smalltalk; Haskell; etc.

Industries: Finance and trading; regulatory issues in banking and insurance; education and training systems; technical certification; business workflow analysis; standards bodies and standards compliance.

REFERENCES

Available upon request.

Recommendations made via linkedin.com are at http://www.linkedin.com/ppl/webprofile?id=5747758.